Guide to the Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning BCMS.0039
Brooklyn Collection
- Subject files, 1933-1957 [bulk 1950-1957]; 1950-1957
  - City Planning: Press clippings (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - City Planning: Proposal Rezoning of NYC: Correspondence, 1949-1955 (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - Civil Defense, 1933-1951 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Community chests (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - Community organization: General (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - Courts reform (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - Day Care: Legislation, 1950-1951 (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - Bensonhurst: Bensonhurst Youth Council (Box 56, Folder 6)
  - Day Care: Press clippings (Box 56, Folder 7)
  - Day Care: Publications (Box 56, Folder 8)
  - Day Care (Box 56, Folder 9)
  - Dental Health (Box 56, Folder 10)
  - Discrimination in education (Box 56, Folder 11)
  - Drug addiction (Box 56, Folder 12)
  - Education (Box 56, Folder 13)
  - Family case work: General (Box 56, Folder 14)
  - Family case work: Press clippings (Box 56, Folder 15)
  - Foster care (Box 56, Folder 16)
  - Floridation: Press clippings (Box 56, Folder 17)
  - Floridation: General, 1954-1957 (Box 56, Folder 18)
  - Floridation: Publications (Box 56, Folder 19)
  - Foundations (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - Handicapped (Box 57, Folder 2)
  - Health: Press clippings (Box 57, Folder 3)
  - Health: Reference material (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - Health Insurance: Group plans (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - Health Insurance: HIP of Greater New York (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - Housing: Brooklyn Needs: General information (Box 57, Folder 7)
  - Housing: Press clippings (Box 57, Folder 8)
  - Housing: Emergency Committee to Save Public Housing: Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 57, Folder 9)
  - Housing: Grand Jury Presentment, 1952 (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - Housing: Publications: Miscellaneous (Box 58, Folder 2)
  - Housing: Publications: Community Service Society of NY (Box 58, Folder 3)
  - Housing: Publications: New York State (Box 58, Folder 4)
  - Housing: Recreation Centers in Housing Projects (Box 58, Folder 5)
  - Housing: Discrimination: General (Box 58, Folder 6)
  - Housing: Discrimination: Sharkey-Issaacs-Brown Bill (NYC Council), 1957 (Box 58, Folder 7)
  - Housing: Discrimination: Sharkey-Issaacs-Brown Bill (NYC Council) - Press clippings, 1957 (Box 58, Folder 8)
  - Immigrants: Services to new immigrants (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - Integration in schools (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - Juvenile Delinquency: Press clippings (Box 59, Folder 3)
  - Juvenile Delinquency: Brooklyn Committee to Combat Juvenile Delinquency (Box 59, Folder 4)
  - Juvenile Delinquency: General (Box 59, Folder 5)
  - Juvenile Delinquency: Hearings (Box 59, Folder 6)
  - Juvenile Delinquency: Prevention (Box 59, Folder 7)
  - Juvenile Delinquency: Publications and reports (Box 59, Folder 8)
  - Legislation: Correspondence with concerned organizations, 1954-1957 (Box 59, Folder 9)
  - Legislations: Press clippings (Box 59, Folder 10)
  - Legislation: Social Legislation Information Service: Bulletin, 1952-1954 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Legislation: Social Legislation Information Service: Bulletin, 1955 (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - Legislation: Social Legislation Information Service: Bulletin, 1956 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - Legislation: State Charities Aid Association, Legislative Information Bureau: Bulletin, 1953-1955 (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - Legislation: State Charities Aid Association, Legislative Information Bureau: Bulletin, 1955 (Box 60, Folder 5)
  - Legislation: State Charities Aid Association, Legislative Information Bureau: Bulletin, 1956 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Legislation: State Charities Aid Association, Legislative Information Bureau: Bulletin, 1957 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Mental Health: National Mental Health Week, 1951 (Box 61, Folder 3)
  - Mental Health: Reports, "Study of Services to Psychotic and Post-Psychotic Patients Living in the Community", 1953 (Box 61, Folder 4)
  - Mental Health Services Act, [New York] State Community (Box 61, Folder 5)
  - Mental Retardation (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - Motion Pictures: General (Box 61, Folder 7)
  - Muscular Dystrophy (Box 61, Folder 8)
  - Narcotics Abuse: Miscellaneous (Box 61, Folder 9)
  - Narcotics Abuse: Press clippings (Box 61, Folder 10-12)
  - Narcotics Abuse: Publications (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - Nutrition: "Dairy Council Digests" (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - Publicity and public relations (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - Public assistance: Press clippings (Box 62, Folder 4)
  - Public assistance: Proposed publication of relief lists, 1952 (Box 62, Folder 5)
  - Public assistance: Reference material (Box 62, Folder 6)
  - Puerto Ricans: Reference material (Box 62, Folder 7)
  - Puerto Ricans: BCSP Report on Puerto Ricans in Brooklyn, 1953 (Box 62, Folder 8)
  - Puerto Ricans: BCSP Workshop Conference, 1953 October 22 (Box 62, Folder 9)
  - Puerto Ricans: Fordham Puerto Rican Study: Listing of Spanish-language (Box 62, Folder 10)
  - Puerto Ricans: General (Box 62, Folder 11)
  - Puerto Ricans: Mayors Committee on Puerto Rican Affairs in NYC (Box 62, Folder 12)
  - Puerto Ricans: Press clippings (Box 62, Folder 13)
    Note
    Organizations and Groups in NYC as of 1 Dec., 1951
  - Puerto Ricans: Press clippings (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - Puerto Ricans: Reference materials II (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Queens (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Race relations: Press clippings (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Race relations (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - Recreation: Miscellaneous (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Recreation: Report, "Recreation Facilities in Brooklyn by Health and Welfare Districts", 1938 (Box 63, Folder 7)
  - Shelters for homeless women (Box 63, Folder 8)
  - Social hygiene (Box 63, Folder 9)
  - Social security (Box 63, Folder 10)
  - Social work (Box 64, Folder 1)
  - Statistics: Children's Bureau, U.S. Dept. of Labor (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - Statistics: Day Care (Box 64, Folder 3)
  - Statistics: Family Welfare (Box 64, Folder 4)
  - Statistics: General (Box 64, Folder 5)
  - Statistics: NYC by Borough (Box 64, Folder 6)
  - Statistics: Non-profit employment bureaus (Box 64, Folder 7)
  - Statistics: Public and private assistance in NYC (Box 64, Folder 8)
  - Statistical Reports: Homeless men (Box 64, Folder 9)
  - Switchblades (Box 64, Folder 10)
  - Tuberculosis (Box 64, Folder 11)
  - Volunteers: Reference material (Box 64, Folder 12)
  - Welfare councils: General (non-NYC) (Box 64, Folder 13)
  - Youth: Miscellaneous (Box 64, Folder 14)
  - Youth: Press clippings: Gangs (Box 64, Folder 15)
  - Youth: Report: "NYC's Million Young People", Conference on Youth Needs, 1945 (Box 64, Folder 16)
  - Youth: Midcentury White House Conference on Children and Youth (Box 64, Folder 17)
  - Youth Court (Box 64, Folder 18)
- BCSP publications, 1939-1957
  Alphabetical by title.
  Included in this series are various annual reports, pamphlets, and directories produced by the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning. Publications cover topics and services of interest to BCSP, including services to the aged, veterans' services, recreation directories, mental health services, and a guide to using the court system. "Welcome to Brooklyn: Handbook for New Workers," (1954, revised 1955) is a comprehensive reference guide for social service workers who are not familiar with the borough (see also, subseries 3.7, Programs: Professional training). It offers a capsule history of Brooklyn, and its political, industrial, educational and cultural resources, as well as a guide to social welfare services. In 1957 this publication was revised as "All About Brooklyn: A Handbook for Brooklynites," and was aimed at social workers and "others who have a stake in the welfare of the borough's citizens...to Board members and other volunteers, to participants in neighborhood organizations, civic and church leaders, etc." Some of these publications will be found in other series (for example, Series 3, Program activities); some publications missing in other series will be found here.
  - Annual Reports: BCSP, 1939-1942/1943 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports: BCSP, 1943/1944-1955 (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports: Brooklyn Nutrition Committee (Box 65, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports: Group Work and Recreation Division (Box 65, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports: Veterans' Affairs Committee (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - Age Will Be Served, 1948 (Box 65, Folder 6)
  - Agencies Offering Services to Brooklyn Veterans, 1944 (Box 65, Folder 7)
  - Aids to Communication from Social Agency to School in Brooklyn, 1952 (Box 65, Folder 8)
  - All About Brooklyn: a handbook for Brooklynites, 1957 (Box 65, Folder 9)
  - BCSP brochure, circa 1945 (Box 65, Folder 10)
  - Brooklyn Health Council; a re-evaluation of its structure, function and program, 1934-1945 (Walter P. Zand), 1949 (Box 65, Folder 11)
  - Brooklyn Recreation Directory [in 8 sections], 1949 (Box 65, Folder 12)
  - A Directory of Mental Hygiene Facilities, 1941 (Box 65, Folder 13)
  - Directory of Resources for Day Care of Children in Brooklyn, undated (Box 65, Folder 14)
  - Growing up in Brooklyn: a report of Brooklyn's Little White House Conference on Children and Youth, 1957 (Box 65, Folder 15)
  - Handbook of Social Welfare Services for Mental Hygiene Workshop on Schools and Agencies, 1948-1949, revised circa 1949-1950 (Box 65, Folder 16)
  - Index to Studies, Surveys and Reports Containing Information relating to Brooklyn, 1925-1940 (Box 65, Folder 17)
  - Look at the Facts, 1946 (Box 65, Folder 18)
  - Mental Hygiene Committee Report of Special Study Committee, Practices in intake of Brooklyn Psychiatric Clinics, 1947 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - New Steps to Mental Health, 1953 (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - Publicity Guide for Social Agencies in Brooklyn, 1950 (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - Report on St. John's Park Project, 1954 (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - Report of Tompkins Park Youth Leadership Project, 1950 (Box 66, Folder 5)
  - Report on Survey of Brooklyn Agencies Rendering Services to Puerto Ricans, 1953 (Box 66, Folder 6)
  - Study of Services to Psychotic and Post-Psychotic Patients Living in the Community, 1953 (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - Summary of Conference on our Expanding Negro Population, 1945 April 6 (Box 66, Folder 8)
  - Summer Fun in Fort Greene Neighborhood, 1950, 1952, 1953 (Box 66, Folder 9)
  - Summer in Williamsburg: directory of recreation and day care programs, 1945 (Box 66, Folder 10)
  - Using Brooklyn's Courts: a guide for social and health agencies, 1956 (Box 66, Folder 11)
  - We Work Together, 1946 (Box 66, Folder 12)
  - Welcome to Brooklyn: handbook for new workers, 1954 October (Box 66, Folder 13)
  - Welcome to Brooklyn: handbook for new workers, 1955 (Box 66, Folder 14)
  - Workshop conference on Puerto Ricans, 1951 (Box 66, Folder 15)
  - Membership directories (Box 66, Folder 16)
  - Report of the Youth Council Project - Green, 1948 (Box 66, Folder 17)
- Press clipping scrapbooks, 1933-1957 [bulk 1933-1950]; 1933-1950
  Chronological.
  Assembled by BCSP staff, these scrapbooks contain press clippings on the activities of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning from its founding until its dissolution in 1957, as well as articles on subjects of concern to the Council (pending social welfare legislation, funding for services, veterans issues, etc.). The pages covering 1933 include minutes of meetings, meeting agendas, and form letters as well. The earliest clippings chronicle the founding of the organization; the last describe its demise. The majority of articles clipped are from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle; other New York City newspapers, including The New York Times are also represented.
  - 1933 January-June (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - 1933 July-1934 (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - 1935-1938 (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 67, Folder 4)
  - 1934-1947 (Box 67, Folder 5)
  - 1948-1950 (Box 67, Folder 6)
  - 1951-1955 (Box 67, Folder 7)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 67, Folder 8)